Financial product advertisements are
often unconcerned with the truth, or in
the words of philosopher Harry
Frankfurt, they are full of
You're probably susceptible to it, too.
A 2022 study found that younger,
high-income men who are very confident
in their own financial knowledge are
more likely to fall for financial
The financial products that
get advertised the most aggressively
tend to be the most profitable for the
firm selling them. If it's highly
profitable for them, you can generally
infer that it is less profitable for
you. You're the one funding the profits,
but the thing is, if you know what to
look for and what to avoid, you can
actually use this to your advantage. I'm
Ben Felix, chief investment officer at
PWL Capital, and I'm going to show you
how financial advertising bullshits you
into buying expensive financial products
and what you can do about it.
Research on financial product
advertising has found that more heavily
advertised products tend to be more
expensive for consumers, that the ads
contain little relevant information, and
that the information they do highlight
is often enticing but irrelevant or at
least incomplete for making a good
decision. This is not an accident.
Financial product advertising
intentionally focuses on
attention-grabbing features while making
the things that actually matter harder
to evaluate. It also pushes up the cost
of financial products themselves without
moving consumers toward better
decision-making. To get a sense of the
scale, one analysis showed that
marketing and distribution expenses are
responsible for about a third of the
cost of actively managed mutual funds.
The authors find that marketing makes
investors worse off overall because
highly marketed funds attract more
assets than they should, and they often
underperform. I think most of you
watching my videos have probably already
figured out that high-fee actively
managed mutual funds can be avoided in
general, regardless of how good the ads
are, and a lot of people have figured
out that low-cost index funds are a
better way to invest, which is
consistent with index funds attracting
more and more assets at the expense of
active funds giving them up while active
funds also dropped their fees. This is
all good news, but the financial
industry has continued to innovate new
ways to generate profits and in many
cases the products being marketed most
aggressively to investors today are far
worse, in my opinion, than the quaint
old days of actively managed mutual
funds. I'm going to talk about the
marketing behind private assets, margin
loans, options trading, thematic ETFs,
and of course covered call ETFs. The ads
for these products are smart. They know
how your brain works. They tend to rely
on five techniques. Once you hear them,
you'll start noticing them everywhere.
Transference borrows credibility from
something real, like the expected growth
of a sector or the income yield of a
covered call fund, and transfers it to
an area where it's irrelevant, like the
expected returns of a product investing
in that sector or using that strategy.
Framing it uses empty language to
associate a product with positive mental
categorizations. Salience highlights
specific attention-grabbing features
that may not be relevant to evaluating
the product, but do grab your interest.
Shrouding buries the things that
actually matter, like fees, costs, and
risks in footnotes and fine print. And
complexity makes products hard to
evaluate. Financial products are often
complex enough to make comparisons
between them nearly impossible. So,
instead of evaluating them properly,
which often takes time and expertise,
you end up defaulting to trust and
intuition, which is being actively
manipulated by the ads themselves.
Together, this creates a powerful
psychological mechanism. You're given
something that feels like compelling
information about a financial product,
but it's often irrelevant or at least
insufficient to decide whether the
product is actually a good investment
for you. It should be no surprise that
when financial product providers spend
marketing dollars to promote products,
they will promote the ones that are most
profitable for them. No one's going to
spend ad dollars to promote a
money-losing product. That just it makes
sense as a business. You got to respect
the hustle. You got to respect that
companies exist to be profitable. But if
it's highly profitable for the firm
selling it, we can generally infer that
it's less profitable for you, the end
consumer. You are funding the profits.
Let's go through some examples. I'll
explain how they're marketed and what
the marketing conveniently leaves out.
If you have other examples that I
missed, tell me about them in the
comments. Private equity and private
credit are increasingly being advertised
to retail investors in Canada. A big
part of the pitch is that private
markets deliver higher returns than
public markets. Some of the most
prominent and heavily marketed pitches
in Canada make this the clear focus of
the advertisement, but the claim is
contestable or at least requires
context. To be clear, it is possible to
show that a private equity index like
this has outperformed public equities
over some time periods. One of the
challenges with these index data is that
they're often based on net asset values,
which are non-market tested values for
the underlying private holdings. It's
basically what the fund says its assets
are worth rather than what it can
actually sell them for, which are often
different numbers. A recent challenge in
private markets has been the inability
of funds to sell their assets for their
net asset values, highlighting an issue
colloquially referred to as return
smoothing or volatility laundering. The
numbers look good on paper, but you
can't actually sell the assets for their
paper values. This can also show up as
illiquidity, where fund investors can't
get their money back when they want it.
Analysis that uses secondary market
transactions in private equity fund
shares, let me explain that. Sometimes
people want to sell the shares they own
in an illiquid private equity fund, and
the researchers used those actual
transaction prices of those private
equity fund shares instead of the fund's
reported net asset values to estimate a
private equity index from 2006 through
2017. The result shows that private
equity's performance is fully explained
by taking on more public equity market
risk than a public equity index. In this
case, roughly double the risk measured
by market beta for buyout funds. Once
this additional risk is accounted for,
the excess risk-adjusted return of the
private equity indices for both buyouts
and venture capital in this analysis are
statistically indistinguishable from
zero. Taking on more risk is not
necessarily a bad thing and it can lead
to outperformance, but it should be
front and center when evaluating an
investment product. And even that's not
the end of the story. Research using a
different performance evaluation method
called the public market equivalent or
PME finds that when consistently defined
and benchmarked, private equity
performed about the same as public
equity from 2006 through June 2025.
I think the jury is still out on
whether, after its high fees and costs,
private equity has a reasonable
expectation of outperforming public
equity. And even if it does, its risks,
including potential illiquidity, need to
be highlighted. Part of the problem is
that measuring private equity
performance is itself complex. The
choice of performance metric, benchmark,
or time period can support claims of
outperformance even if it's not a
reasonable expectation. Looking at the
fund from the marketing example, while
it's only been around since 2024, it has
returned, in line with the research I
just mentioned, about the same as a
public equity index fund. Anecdotally, I
do get the sense that people are waking
up to the realities of the private
equity sales pitch. At PWL Capital,
we've been seeing more and more people
coming to us asking for help unwinding
their illiquid and often underperforming
private equity positions. Private credit
has similar issues. Private credit
consists of loans to private companies,
kind of like bonds, except the loans are
not publicly traded and are created by
non-bank entities like private credit
funds or business development companies.
These funds raise money from investors
and make direct loans, often with
flexible terms and covenants, to private
companies. These loans, by their nature,
are risky. Like private equity, private
credit funds are illiquid and will not
have their assets marked to market
daily. This allows them to appear
relatively low risk and uncorrelated to
other assets, even if the value of their
underlying assets would be fluctuating
wildly in the public markets. And again,
like private equity, when the returns on
private credit funds are properly
evaluated against risk-appropriate
benchmarks and adjusted for their
illiquidity, there's nothing special
there in terms of risk-adjusted returns
or diversification. One of the big
problems I see with private credit is
that it's often marketed based on its
yield. That's salience at work.
Investors love the idea of passive
income, sitting back and collecting cash
flow. The problem, especially with
high-risk loans like what we see in
private credit, is that yield and total
return, which to be clear is what
actually matters, total return,
yield and total return have a messy
relationship. Due to the value of the
loans being volatile and some loans
going bust entirely, total returns in
credit investments tend to trail their
headline yield. We see this clearly with
the example advertisement where the
target yield is 9.6%, but the realized
total return since inception in 2023 is
7.7%,
which is in line with a publicly-traded
high-yield bond ETF. Private assets are
risky, illiquid, and expensive to own.
Ads claiming that they generate returns
superior to publicly-listed assets or
offer a unique source of diversification
are contested by academic research. And
at the very least, any claims about
their higher expected returns should
highlight their higher risk. None of
this is obvious from the marketing
materials, which could lead an investor
to allocate to the products when they
otherwise would not have or to allocate
more than they would have if the full
set of information had been available.
And here's the kicker. Like many of the
heavily advertised products I'll talk
about, private investments are often
lucrative for those selling them. Many
of these funds will pay wealth managers
who invest their clients' money in the
fund. Think about it. If you're a wealth
manager, I can speak to this from
experience. I know what it's like. If
you're a wealth manager and can get a
kickback from placing your clients'
assets into a private market fund,
increasing your revenue from that
client, it starts to sound like a pretty
smart idea. Having worked in financial
services for more than a decade, I get
it. I know what it's like. It's not easy
to see past the dollars. It's possible,
as firms like PWL Capital show, we don't
take money from the funds that we invest
in, but it's not easy. The money is
there. The Financial Times has reported
that billions of dollars have been paid
from private market funds to the banks
and brokerages offering them to their
clients, creating an incentive to
promote those products over something
like a low-cost index fund, which does
not have any kickbacks or incentives for
placing clients' money in them. Another
way that this can show up is through the
wealth manager negotiating a lower fee
from the private fund manager and
pocketing the difference or a portion of
the difference between the fund's normal
fee paid by clients and the lower
negotiated fee. Even if some of that fee
is returned to customers, there is a
clear incentive to recommend the private
fund over a low-cost index fund. The
heavy marketing pitch starts to make a
lot more sense when you follow the
money. That's private markets, where the
story for higher returns sounds great,
but the reality is much less compelling,
and those selling the products, rather
than those investing in them, stand to
reap most of the benefits. Something
that you will reap all of the benefits
from is subscribing to this channel if
you have not already done so. The next
product I want to talk about is being
marketed based on its power. But power
cuts both ways. This is an example of
framing, empty language designed to get
you into positive mental frame when
thinking about the product. Margin
investing, which means borrowing from
your brokerage using your investments as
collateral, is often promoted to retail
investors as a way to boost returns.
Discount brokers are, in many cases, not
charging their customers commissions for
trades anymore, which used to be how
they made a lot of their money, which
has made marginal loan interest an
increasingly important part of their
revenue. I've seen margin marketed to
retail investors through email marketing
campaigns and flashy landing pages that
focus on the power of margin, which to
be clear is a real thing, but without
much of a focus on the associated risks.
It's worth going deeper on the truth to
the statement on the truth about the
power of margin. Borrowing to invest,
when done responsibly, is not inherently
a bad thing, and it may even be the
right thing for some people to do as
long as it's done as part of a long-term
plan. However, investing on margin
introduces a lot of risk, and it's
associated with negative financial
behaviors. The empirical reality, like
what actually happens among retail
investors, is that margin tends to be
used by overconfident investors who
trade frequently and perform poorly. A
2020 study found that investors with
margin accounts trade more actively,
more speculatively, and importantly less
profitably than those with cash
accounts, and that among investors who
have margin accounts, those with
experience trading on margin, again,
trade more actively, more speculatively,
and less profitably. Despite these
empirical realities, 20% of Canadian
retail investors surveyed in 2020
reported using leverage to invest.
Focusing on the opportunity or power of
margin without highlighting the risks
and empirical realities is, in my
opinion, incomplete and could lead
investors down a path that is profitable
for their brokerage because they're now
paying margin interest, but not for
them. I suspect that the reason we see
so many ads for margin, again, is that
margin lending is a major revenue driver
for brokerages, especially when they've
eliminated trading commissions. There's
another revenue source that's probably
even more lucrative and definitely
marketed more aggressively. I can't
scroll Reddit for more than a few
minutes without seeing ads for options
trading. The ads focus on the
opportunity, again, positive framing,
and on low fees, which I'm going to call
transference or borrowing credibility
from the positive attribute of low fees,
while shrouding the total trading costs,
particularly for trading US options. The
first omission is that US options trades
are often sold to market makers in an
arrangement called payment for order
flow. This practice is not allowed
within Canada, but US options,
obviously, trade in the US. By selling
the order flow, brokerages have been
able to drive commissions down often to
zero since they receive significant
revenue from selling the order flow. Low
commissions are good, but they're not
the whole story. Within stocks, payment
for order flow seems to be an overall
good thing for investors because it
drove commissions down and trade
execution seems to be good.
But less so in options, where payment
for order flow seems to be related to
wider spreads. That aside, I think
there's a bigger problem here. Payment
for options order flow is far more
lucrative for brokerages than payment
for stock order flow, creating an
incentive for brokers to promote options
trading to their clients. To be clear,
options are not inherently a bad thing.
It's kind of like margin. They're useful
tools for many reasons, and the
technology and its underlying
mathematics have arguably changed the
world for the better. While they can be
used for good, some of their features,
like embedded leverage, make them a
double-edged sword. They can just as
easily be used for responsible risk
management and hedging as they can be
used for speculation and gambling. For
retail investors, again, I want to come
back to the empirical reality, which is
on the wrong edge of the sword. A 2023
paper estimates that the aggregate
portfolio of retail investors lost $2.1
billion trading options from November
2019 to June 2021, largely due to
indirect trading costs. That retail
option traders lost money on average,
and that 50% of retail trades in the
sample are in risky options with less
than a week to expiration, with an
average quoted bid-ask spread of 12.6
percent. A study on 68,000 trading
accounts and more than 8 million trades
in stocks and options at a large online
broker in the Netherlands similarly
finds that most investors take
significant losses on their options
trades much larger than the losses they
take from equity trading. Ads focusing
on the explicit costs of option trades,
low or zero commissions, which is a real
thing, without explaining the often high
implicit costs, wide bid-ask spreads,
and positioning options trades as an
opportunity to get ahead when
empirically most retail investors lose
on their options trades could lead
people to make bad decisions. Thematic
ETF advertising tends to highlight an
exciting theme that investors are
currently interested in. We're going to
space, which could be a big deal,
legitimately, and investors don't want
to miss out on the opportunity. That
very real economic opportunity is used
to market an investment product, but
it's not relevant in that context. The
problem is that thematic ETFs tend to
launch after the theme they represent
has already delivered high returns when
investor interest is high and then go on
to deliver poor performance, often
resulting in the fund closing down.
Research commissioned by the Financial
Times shows that the vast majority of
thematic ETFs have underperformed broad
market benchmarks. A 2021 academic study
found the thematic ETFs underperformed
by 6% on average in the 5 years after
launching, despite their themes having
strong performance before launch, which
is part of the problem. ETF companies
like to launch these funds because they
can charge higher fees than they could
with a low-cost index fund, and unlike
with index funds, investors in these
products are fee insensitive. Investors
in index funds care about fees, but in
thematic funds, they don't. This paper
shows that in 2019, this is a while ago
now, thematic ETF made up 18% of the ETF
market but accounted for about 35% of
the industry's revenues. Despite their
higher fees, again, investors are eager
to buy these products because they're
excited about the theme. They don't care
about the fees. But the problem is it
doesn't tend to work out well.
Morningstar's Global Thematic Fund
Landscape 2025 finds that the long-term
odds of picking a thematic fund that
both survives and outperforms global
equities is very low. The data for
Canadian listed funds is even more
damning with 100% of Canadian listed
thematic funds either closing or
underperforming at the 10-year horizon
and 100% of funds closing by the 15-year
mark. The underlying reasons for this
poor performance are kind of simple. I
mean, we could get more complex, but the
simple explanation is that exciting
growth that you expect from a theme,
like space,
is usually already reflected in high
stock prices for that theme. As reality
unfolds, expectations tend to settle
down and stock prices tend to fall. This
cycle has repeated countless times
throughout history. Every time there's a
new exciting technology, and each time
it happens, financial intermediaries
find a way to profit off of it by
selling financial products. Another type
of ETF that I see heavily marketed
online, both in ads and through
influencers, is covered call ETFs. A
covered call means selling a call
option, that is the right to buy the
stock from you at a predetermined price,
called the strike
in exchange for a premium, and you're
selling this call on a stock that you
own, which puts a cap on your upside
returns. A fund using this strategy
typically distributes the option
premiums from selling calls to the fund
investors, resulting in high
distribution yields.
Now, some people like that, fair enough,
but I've got more to say. Those
distribution yields are heavily
marketed. That That is the focus of the
marketing, but this specific data point
is, in my opinion, misleading due to the
relationship between option premium
income and total expected returns,
expected total returns. Selling the call
is only the first step in the trade. The
fund has sold the right to buy the
underlying stock at the strike price. If
the price of the underlying rises above
the strike price, the option holder,
whoever the fund sold the option to,
will exercise their call option, and the
fund will have to sell the stock at a
price below its market value. That's
putting that cap that I mentioned on
upside returns. In some ways covered
calls look a lot like a mix of stocks
and cash, which most long-term investors
realize is not a great way to allocate
assets. The overall result is that
selling the call has reduced exposure to
the underlying equity primarily on the
upside, while the downside remains
largely exposed, reducing expected
returns and capping the ability of the
fund to recover after the inevitable
downturns that stocks experience over
time.
For long-term investors, my view is that
covered call funds are not good
investments in general, do not generate
passive income, and create unnecessary
layers of risk and costs.
Critically, this is also true for
investors who need income. As I've shown
in past analyses, they are better off
owning the underlying and selling bits
and pieces of the portfolio as needed.
But, covered call funds charge higher
fees than index funds, and so they get
heavily marketed. The threads connecting
everything I've covered in this video
are information or the lack thereof and
incentives. In every case, the ads are
not lying. They're providing
information that is real. They're just
not giving you what you need to make a
good decision. Instead, they're
persuading you to buy a product that is
highly profitable for the firm selling
it while having questionable value to
you. It should be no surprise that when
financial firms spend marketing dollars,
they promote the products that are most
profitable for them. I I respect that.
It makes sense for a business to do
that, but you don't have to fall for it.
You can be a savvy consumer and use this
knowledge to your advantage. The crazy
thing is that a lot of people will fall
for these ads. That's why we see them.
The ads are clearly working. And that
fact is powerful for you to understand.
Consumers who understand the cost and
pitfalls of heavily marketed financial
products like what I've talked about
stand to benefit from low-cost loss
leader services like free trading and
ultra low-cost index funds that
financial firms can provide because they
expect to generate profits from more
lucrative channels like getting a cut
from private fund fees, charging margin
interest, receiving payment for US order
flow, and charging higher fees on
thematic or covered call ETFs. If you
can stay disciplined and avoid getting
sucked into these more profitable for
the financial firms products, you are
effectively receiving a subsidy from
less financially sophisticated
consumers. Harsh, but that's the reality
we live in. The funds that I find most
sensible don't tend to advertise at all,
which probably helps to explain their
low fees. You can learn more about
Dimensional Fund Advisors here and
Avantis, who recently launched ETFs in
Canada, here. I gain nothing from you
knowing about those fund companies or
those products other than the
satisfaction that you're less likely to
buy covered call ETFs.